<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - GAMBLING ROOM - NIGHT
Jan sits at the roulette table. He has only three chips left and seems bewildered.
As Rick comes up the croupier speaks to Jan.
CROUPIER
Do you wish to place another bet, sir?
JAN
No, no, I guess not.
Rick stands behind Jan.
RICK
to Jan
Have you tried twenty-two tonight? I said, twenty-two.
Jan looks at Rick, then at the chips in his hand.
He pauses, then puts the chips on twenty-two.
Rick and the croupier exchange looks. The croupier understands what Rick wants him to do. He spins the wheel.
Carl follows the proceedings, fascinated.
The wheel stops spinning.
CROUPIER
in French
Twenty-two, black, twenty-two.
A winner. Renault, at a nearby table, takes notice of what is happening.
The croupier pushes a pile of chips onto twenty-two and Jan reaches for it.
RICK
not even looking at Jan
Leave it there.
Jan hesitates, then withdraws his hands.
Carl continues to watch.
The wheel spins. Nobody speaks while it spins. It stops.
CROUPIER
Twenty-two, black.
Another winner. The croupier shoves a pile of chips toward Jan.
RICK
to Jan
Cash it in and don't come back.
Jan rises to go to the cashier.
A CUSTOMER complains to Carl.
CUSTOMER
Say, are you sure this place is honest?
CARL
fervently
Honest! As honest as the day is long!
Meanwhile, Rick has walked over to the croupier.
RICK
How we doing tonight?
CROUPIER
Well, a couple of thousand less than I thought there would be.
Rick smiles slightly and goes toward the door.
Annina runs up to him and hugs him.
ANNINA
Monsieur Rick, I --
RICK
-- He's just a lucky guy.
CARL
solicitously
Monsieur Rick, may I get you a cup of coffee?
RICK
No thanks, Carl.
CARL
Monsieur Rick!
Renault, seeing that Jan has won, gets up from his table to follow Rick. Jan and Annina stop him on the way.
JAN
Captain Renault, may I --
RENAULT
-- Oh, not here, please. Come to my office in the morning. We'll do everything business-like.
JAN
We'll be there at six.
RENAULT
I'll be there at ten. I am very happy for both of you. Still, it's very strange that you won.
He looks over and sees Rick.
RENAULT
Well, maybe not so strange. I'll see you in the morning.
ANNINA
Thank you so much, Captain Renault.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
At the bar, Carl whispers in Sacha's ear. Sacha says "No!" and runs to Rick.
SACHA
Boss, you've done a beautiful thing.
He kisses Rick on both cheeks.
RICK
Go away, you crazy Russian!
Carl pours a brandy for Rick.
Pretending not to do so, Rick glances in Ilsa's direction. Renault comes up to him.
RENAULT
As I suspected, you're a rank sentimentalist.
RICK
Yeah? Why?
RENAULT
chidingly
Why do you interfere with my little romances?
RICK
Put it down as a gesture to love.
RENAULT
good-naturedly
Well, I forgive you this time. But I'll be in tomorrow night with a breathtaking blonde, and it will make me very happy if she loses. Uh huh!
He smiles and walks away. Laszlo comes up to Rick.
LASZLO
Monsieur Blaine, I wonder if I could talk to you?
RICK
Go ahead.
LASZLO
Well, isn't there some other place? It's rather confidential, what I have to say.
RICK
My office.
LASZLO
Right.
DISSOLVE TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - OFFICE - NIGHT
Rick and Laszlo sit and discuss Laszlo's dilemma.
LASZLO
You must know it's very important I get out of Casablanca. It's my privilege to be one of the leaders of a great movement. You know what I have been doing. You know what it means to the work, to the lives of thousands and thousands of people that I be free to reach America and continue my work.
RICK
I'm not interested in politics. The problems of the world are not in my department. I'm a saloon keeper.
LASZLO
My friends in the underground tell me that you have quite a record. You ran guns to Ethiopia. You fought against the fascists in Spain.
RICK
What of it?
LASZLO
Isn't it strange that you always happened to be fighting on the side of the underdog?
RICK
Yes. I found that a very expensive hobby, too. But then I never was much of a businessman.
Rick gets up, as does Laszlo.
LASZLO
Are you enough of a businessman to appreciate an offer of a hundred thousand francs?
RICK
I appreciate it, but I don't accept it.
LASZLO
I'll raise it to two hundred thousand.
RICK
My friend, you could make it a million francs, or three, my answer would still be the same.
LASZLO
There must be some reason why you won't let me have them.
RICK
There is. I suggest that you ask your wife.
LASZLO
I beg your pardon?
RICK
I said, ask your wife.
LASZLO
My wife?
Laszlo looks at him, puzzled.
RICK
Yes.
Rick and Laszlo hear MALE VOICES singing downstairs.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
A group of German officers stand around the piano singing the "Wacht am Rhein."
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - BALCONY - NIGHT
Rick stands at the balcony outside his office and watches the Germans below.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
At the bar, Renault watches with raised eyebrow.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - BALCONY - NIGHT
Laszlo's lips are very tight as he listens to the song.
He starts down the step.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
Laszlo passes the table where Ilsa sits and goes straight to the orchestra.
Yvonne, sitting at a table with her German officer, stares down into her drink.
Laszlo speaks to the orchestra.
LASZLO
Play the Marseillaise! Play it!
Members of the orchestra glance toward the steps, toward Rick, who nods to them.
Laszlo and Corina sing as they start to play. Strasser conducts the German singing in an attempt to drown out the competition.
People in the cafe begin to sing the "Marseillaise."
After a while, Strasser and his officers give up and sit down. The "Marseillaise" continues, however.
Yvonne jumps up and sings with tears in her eyes.
Ilsa, overcome with emotion, looks proudly at Laszlo, who sings with passion.
Finally the whole cafe stands, singing, their faces aglow. The song finishes on a high, triumphant note.
Yvonne's face is exalted. She deliberately faces the alcove where the Germans are watching. She SHOUTS at the top of her lungs.
YVONNE
Vive La France! Vive la democracie!
CROWD
Vive La France! Vive la democracie!
People clap and cheer.
Strasser is very angry. He strides across the floor toward Renault who is standing at the bar.
STRASSER
You see what I mean? If Laszlo's presence in a cafe can inspire this unfortunate demonstration, what more will his presence in Casablanca bring on? I advise that this place be shut up at once.
RENAULT
innocently
But everybody's having such a good time.
STRASSER
Yes, much too good a time. The place is to be closed.
RENAULT
But I have no excuse to close it.
STRASSER
snapping
Find one.
Several French officers surround Laszlo, offering him a drink.
Renault thinks a moment, then blows a loud BLAST on his whistle. The room grows quiet, all eyes turn toward Renault.
RENAULT
loudly
Everybody is to leave here immediately! This cafe is closed until further notice! Clear the room at once!
An angry murmur starts among the crowd. People get up and begin to leave.
Rick comes quickly up to Renault.
RICK
How can you close me up? On what grounds?
RENAULT
I am shocked, shocked to find that gambling is going on in here!
This display of nerve leaves Rick at a loss. The croupier comes out of the gambling room and up to Renault. He hands him a roll of bills.
CROUPIER
Your winnings, sir.
RENAULT
Oh. Thank you very much.
He turns to the crowd again.
RENAULT
Everybody out at once!
As the cafe empties, Strasser approaches Ilsa. His manner is abrupt but cordial.
STRASSER
Mademoiselle, after this disturbance it is not safe for Laszlo to stay in Casablanca.
ILSA
This morning you implied it was not safe for him to leave Casablanca.
STRASSER
That is also true, except for one destination, to return to occupied France.
ILSA
Occupied France?
STRASSER
Uh huh. Under a safe conduct from me.
ILSA
with intensity
What value is that? You may recall what German guarantees have been worth in the past.
STRASSER
There are only two other alternatives for him.
ILSA
What are they?
STRASSER
It is possible the French authorities will find a reason to put him in the concentration camp here.
ILSA
And the other alternative?
STRASSER
My dear Mademoiselle, perhaps you have already observed that in Casablanca, human life is cheap. Good night, Mademoiselle.
She looks at him, understanding what he means.
He bows and exits as Laszlo arrives at the table.
They start out of the cafe.
ILSA
What happened with Rick?
LASZLO
We'll discuss it later.
CUT TO:
INT. HOTEL HALLWAY - NIGHT
Ilsa and Laszlo walk to their room.
CUT TO:
INT. HOTEL ROOM - NIGHT
Laszlo switches on the light as they enter. While Ilsa takes off some jewelry he walks to the window and peers out into the darkeness. Below and across the street, a man stands under an arch. Laszlo watches him, then draws down the shade.
LASZLO
Our faithful friend is still there.
ILSA
Victor, please, don't go to the underground meeting tonight.
LASZLO
soberly
I must. Besides, it isn't often that a man has a chance to display heroics before his wife.
He crosses to a table, takes a cigarette from a box, and strikes a match.
ILSA
Don't joke. After Major Strasser's warning tonight, I am frightened.
LASZLO
To tell you the truth, I am frightened too. Shall I remain here in our hotel room hiding, or shall I carry on the best I can?
He lights the cigarette.
ILSA
Whatever I'd say, you'd carry on. Victor, why don't you tell me about Rick? What did you find out?
LASZLO
Apparently he has the letters.
ILSA
Yes?
LASZLO
But no intention of selling them. One would think if sentiment wouldn't persuade him, money would.
Ilsa is now noticeably uncomfortable.
ILSA
Did he give any reason?
LASZLO
He suggested I ask you.
ILSA
Ask me?
LASZLO
Yes. He said, "Ask your wife." I don't know why he said that.
Laszlo turns off the light. Ilsa walks over to the couch and sits down.
LASZLO
Well, our friend outside will think we've retired by now. I'll be going in a few minutes.
He sits down on the couch next to her. A silence falls between them. It grows strained. Finally.
LASZLO
Ilsa, I --
ILSA
-- Yes?
LASZLO
When I was in the concentration camp, were you lonely in Paris?
Ilsa still cannot look at him.
ILSA
Yes, Victor, I was.
LASZLO
sympathetically
I know how it is to be lonely.
very quietly
Is there anything you wish to tell me?
ILSA
speaking low
No, Victor, there isn't.
LASZLO
I love you very much, my dear.
Ilsa finally turns to look at Laszlo.
ILSA
Yes, Yes I know. Victor, whatever I do, will you believe that I, that --
LASZLO
-- You don't even have to say it. I'll believe. Goodnight, dear.
He bends down and kisses her cheek.
ILSA
Goodnight.
She watches him go.
ILSA
Victor!
She gets up and follows him to the door. He opens it. In the slit of light from the hall we see Ilsa's face, now strained and worried. She hesitates for a moment, then.
ILSA
Be careful.
LASZLO
Of course, I'll be careful.
He kisses her on the cheek and goes out the door. She stands there for a few seconds, then crosses to look out of the window.
The figure in the archway is gone. She sees Victor walking down the street and closes the blind again. Ilsa gets a cloak from the bedroom, and leaves the hotel room.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
Rick and Carl sit by the bar and look over ledgers. Carl is busy figuring. He looks up at Rick.
CARL
Well, you are in pretty good shape, Herr Rick.
RICK
How long can I afford to stay closed?
CARL
Oh, two weeks, maybe three.
RICK
Maybe I won't have to. A bribe has worked before. In the meantime, everybody stays on salary.
CARL
Oh, thank you, Herr Rick. Sacha will be happy to hear it. I owe him money.
Carl laughs.
RICK
Now you finish locking up, will you, Carl?
CARL
I will. Then I am going to the meeting of the --
RICK
interrupting
-- Don't tell me where you're going.
CARL
I won't.
RICK
Goodnight.
CARL
Goodnight, Monsieur Rick.
Rick walks up the stairs to his apartment.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - APARTMENT - NIGHT
Rick opens the door and goes inside the dark room. Light from the hall reveals a figure by the window. He lights a small lamp. Ilsa faces him, her face white but determined.
Rick pauses for a moment in astonishment.
RICK
How did you get in?
ILSA
The stairs from the street.
Ilsa comes over to meet him.
RICK
I told you this morning you'd come around, but this is a little ahead of schedule. Well, won't you sit down?
ILSA
Richard, I had to see you.
RICK
You use "Richard" again? We're back in Paris.
ILSA
Please.
RICK
Your unexpected visit isn't connected by any chance with the letters of transit? It seems that as long as I have those letters I'll never be lonely.
ILSA
You can ask any price you want, but you must give me those letters.
RICK
I went through all that with your husband. It's no deal.
ILSA
I know how you feel about me, but I'm asking you to put your feelings aside for something more important.
RICK
Do I have to hear again what a great man your husband is? What an important cause he's fighting for?
ILSA
It was your cause, too. In your own way, you were fighting for the same thing.
RICK
I'm not fighting for anything anymore, except myself. I'm the only cause I'm interested in.
He walks over to the window and Ilsa follows.
ILSA
Richard, Richard, we loved each other once. If those days meant anything at all to you --
RICK
interrupting, harshly
-- I wouldn't bring up Paris if I were you. It's poor salesmanship.
ILSA
Please. Please listen to me. If you knew what really happened, if you only knew the truth --
RICK
cutting in
-- I wouldn't believe you, no matter what you told me. You'd say anything now to get what you want.
Rick walks over to a table and opens a cigarette box, but finds it empty.
ILSA
You want to feel sorry for yourself, don't you? With so much at stake, all you can think of is your own feelings. One woman has hurt you, and you take revenge on the rest of the world. You're a, you're a coward, and a weakling.
There are tears in her eyes now.
ILSA
No. Oh, Richard, I'm sorry. I'm sorry, but, but you, you are our last hope. If you don't help us, Victor Laszlo will die in Casablanca.
RICK
What of it? I'm going to die in Casablanca. It's a good spot for it.
He turns away to light a cigarette, then back to Ilsa.
RICK
Now if you --
He stops short as he sees Ilsa holding a small revolver in her hand. It's pointed directly at him.
ILSA
-- All right. I tried to reason with you. I tried everything. Now I want those letters. Get them for me.
RICK
I don't have to. I've got them right here.
ILSA
Put them on the table.
RICK
shaking his head
No.
ILSA
For the last time, put them on the table.
RICK
If Laszlo and the cause mean so much to you, you won't stop at anything. All right, I'll make it easier for you.
He moves closer to her.
RICK
Go ahead and shoot. You'll be doing me a favor.
Her hand drops down, and there are tears in her eyes again.
She turns and walks away from him.
ILSA
Richard, I tried to stay away. I thought I would never see you again, that you were out of my life.
Rick follows her and takes her in his arms. He presses her tight to him.
ILSA
The day you left, if you knew what I went through! If you knew how much I loved you, how much I still love you!
Rick kisses her passionately. She is lost in his embrace.
DISSOLVE TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - APARTMENT - LATER
From his window, Rick watches the revolving beacon light at the airport.
Ilsa sits on the couch. On a table before her rests a bottle of champagne along with two half-filled glasses.
Rick walks over to her.
RICK
And then?
ILSA
It wasn't long after we were married that Victor went back to Czechoslovakia. They needed him in Prague, but there the Gestapo were waiting for him. Just a two-line item in the paper: "Victor Laszlo apprehended. Sent to concen-tration camp." I was frantic. For months I tried to get word. Then it came. He was dead, shot trying to escape. I was lonely. I had nothing. Not even hope. Then I met you.
RICK
Why weren't you honest with me? Why did you keep your marriage a secret?
Rick sits down with Ilsa.
ILSA
Oh, it wasn't my secret, Richard. Victor wanted it that way. Not even our closest friends knew about our marriage. That was his way of protecting me. I knew so much about his work, and if the Gestapo found out I was his wife it would be dangerous for me and for those working with me.
RICK
When did you first find out he was alive?
ILSA
Just before you and I were to leave Paris together. A friend came and told me that Victor was alive. They were hiding him in a freight car on the outskirts of Paris. He was sick, he needed me. I wanted to tell you, but I, I didn't care. I knew, I knew you wouldn't have left Paris, and the Gestapo would have caught you. So I-- well, well, you know the rest.
RICK
Huh. But it's still a story without an ending. What about now?
ILSA
Now? I don't know. I know that I'll never have the strength to leave you again.
RICK
And Laszlo?
ILSA
Oh, you'll help him now, Richard, won't you? You'll see that he gets out? Then he'll have his work, all that he's been living for.
RICK
All except one. He won't have you.
Ilsa puts her head on Rick's shoulder.
ILSA
I can't fight it anymore. I ran away from you once. I can't do it again. Oh, I don't know what's right any longer. You'll have to think for both of us, for all of us.
RICK
All right, I will. Here's looking at you, kid.
ILSA
I wish I didn't love you so much.
She snuggles closer to Rick.
CUT TO:
EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT
Laszlo and Carl make their way through the darkness toward a side entrance of Rick's. They run inside the entryway.
The headlights of a speeding police car sweep toward them.
They flatten themselves against a wall to avoid detection. The lights move past them.
CARL
I think we lost them.
LASZLO
Yes. I'm afraid they caught some of the others.
CARL
Come inside. Come.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
Laszlo and Carl enter and cross toward the bar, out of breath from their exertion.
CARL
Come inside. I will help you. Come in here.
LASZLO
Thank you.
Carl goes behind the bar.
CARL
I will give you some water.
CUT TO:
INT/EXT. RICK'S CAFE - APARTMENT - NIGHT
Rick and Ilsa hear voices below. Rick crosses to the door. He opens it just enough to see below, and turns off the light.
Ilsa stands just in back of him. She makes a move as if to go out to the balcony but Rick's pushes her back. She withdraws behind the door.
Rick walks out to the balcony railing.
INT. RICK'S CAFE - BALCONY - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
Rick sees Carl attending to Laszlo, who appears to be injured.
RICK
Carl, what happened?
Both Carl and Laszlo look up.
CARL
excitedly
The police break up our meeting. Herr Rick! We escaped in the last moment.
RICK
Come up here a minute.
Carl looks up wonderingly, then starts toward the stairway.
CARL
Yes, I come.
RICK
I want you to turn out the light in the rear entrance. It might attract the police.
CARL
But Sacha always puts out that light --
RICK
-- Tonight he forgot.
CARL
Yes, I come, I will do it.
Carl climbs the stairs.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - APARTMENT - NIGHT
Carl enters Rick's apartment and sees Ilsa. He looks at Rick and says nothing.
RICK
in a low voice
I want you to take Miss Lund home.
CARL
Yes, sir.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
Rick comes down the stairs. Laszlo wraps one of the small bar towels around his cut wrist. Rick looks questioningly at the injured hand.
LASZLO
It's nothing. Just a little cut. We had to get through a window.
Rick walks to the bar, picks up a bottle, and pours a drink.
RICK
Well, this might come in handy.
LASZLO
Thank you.
RICK
Had a close one, eh?
LASZLO
Yes, rather.
Laszlo takes a drink.
RICK
Don't you sometimes wonder if it's worth all this? I mean what you're fighting for?
LASZLO
We might as well question why we breathe. If we stop breathing, we'll die. If we stop fighting our enemies, the world will die.
RICK
What of it? Then it'll be out of it's misery.
Rick reaches in his jacket for his cigarette case, opens it, and takes out a cigarette.
LASZLO
You know how you sound, Monsieur Blaine? Like a man who's trying to convince himself of something he doesn't believe in his heart. Each of us has a destiny, for good or for evil.
RICK
Yes, I get the point.
Rick lights his cigarette.
LASZLO
I wonder if you do. I wonder if you know that you're trying to escape from yourself and that you'll never succeed.
RICK
You seem to know all about my destiny.
LASZLO
I know a good deal more about you than you suspect. I know, for instance, that you are in love with a woman. It is perhaps strange that we both should be in love with the same woman. The first evening I came here in this cafe, I knew there was something between you and Ilsa. Since no one is to blame, I, I demand no explanation. I ask only one thing. You won't give me the letters of transit. All right. But I want my wife to be safe. I ask you as a favor to use the letters to take her away from Casablanca.
RICK
You love her that much?
LASZLO
Apparently you think of me only as the leader of a cause. Well, I am also a human being.
He looks away for a moment.
LASZLO
Yes, I love her that much.
Suddenly there is a CRASH at the door of the cafe, followed by the forced entry of several gendarmes. A French officer walks in and addresses Laszlo.
FRENCH OFFICER
Mr. Laszlo?
LASZLO
Yes?
FRENCH OFFICER
You will come with us. We have a warrant for your arrest.
LASZLO
On what charge?
FRENCH OFFICER
Captain Renault will discuss that with you later.
RICK
It seems that destiny has taken a hand.
Laszlo looks for a moment at Rick, then in dignified silence crosses to the officer. Together they walk toward the door.
Rick's eyes follow them, but his expression reveals nothing of his feelings.
CUT TO:
INT. RENAULT'S OFFICE - MORNING
Renault sits at his desk and smokes while Rick nervously fingers his hat. They're interrupted by an orderly.
Renault hands some forms to the orderly, who then exits, and the conversation continues.
RICK
But you haven't any actual proof, and you know it. This isn't Germany or occupied France. All you can do is fine him a few thousand francs and give him thirty days. You might as well let him go now.
RENAULT
Ricky, I'd advise you not to be too interested in what happens to Laszlo. If by any chance you were to help him escape --
RICK
-- What makes you think I'd stick my neck out for Laszlo?
RENAULT
Because one, you've bet ten thousand francs he'd escape. Two, you have the letters of transit, now don't bother to deny it. And, well, you might do it simply because you don't like Strasser's looks. As a matter of fact, I don't like him either.
RICK
Well, they're all excellent reasons.
RENAULT
Don't count too much on my friendship, Ricky. In this matter I'm powerless. Besides, I might lose ten thousand francs.
RICK
You're not very subtle, but you are effective. I, I get the point. Yes, I have the letters, but I intend using them myself. I'm leaving Casablanca on tonight's plane, the last plane.
RENAULT
Huh?
RICK
And I'm taking a friend with me. One you'll appreciate.
RENAULT
What friend?
RICK
Ilsa Lund.
pause
That ought to put your mind to rest about my helping Laszlo escape. The last man I want to see in America.
RENAULT
You didn't come here to tell me this. You have the letters of transit. You can fill in your name and hers and leave any time you please. Why are you interested in what happens to Laszlo?
Renault gets out of his chair and crosses to the front of his desk.
RICK
I'm not. But I am interested in what happens to Ilsa and me. We have a legal right to go, that's true. But people have been held in Casablanca in spite of their legal rights.
Renault retrieves a fresh cigarette from a box on his desk.
RENAULT
What makes you think we want to hold you?
Renault chain-lights his new cigarette with the old one.
RICK
Ilsa is Laszlo's wife. She probably knows things that Strasser would like to know. Louis, I'll make a deal with you. Instead of this petty charge you have against him, you can get something really big, something that would chuck him in a concentration camp for years. That would be quite a feather in your cap, wouldn't it?
RENAULT
It certainly would. Germany-- Vichy would be very grateful.
RICK
Then release him. You be at my place a half hour before the plane leaves.
Renault sits back down in his chair.
RICK
I'll arrange to have Laszlo come there to pick up the letters of transit, and that'll give you the criminal grounds on which to make the arrest. You get him, and we get away. To the Germans that last will be just a minor annoyance.
RENAULT
puzzled
There's still something about this business I don't quite understand. Miss Lund, she's very beautiful, yes, but you were never interested in any woman.
RICK
Well, she isn't just any woman.
Rick stares at the floor, then looks back up at Renault.
RENAULT
I see. How do I know you'll keep your end of the bargain?
RICK
I'll make the arrangements right now with Laszlo in the visitor's pen.
RENAULT
Ricky, I'm going to miss you. Apparently you're the only one in Casablanca who has even less scruples than I.
RICK
Oh, thanks.
RENAULT
Go ahead, Ricky.
Renault presses a button on his desk, triggering a BUZZER.
The door to Renault's office opens. Rick rises to go.
RICK
And by the way, call off your watchdogs when you let him go. I don't want them around this afternoon. I'm taking no chances, Louis, not even with you.
CUT TO:
INT. THE BLUE PARROT - DAY
A waiter brings tea to Rick and Ferrari, who sit alone at a table in a secluded nook off the main room.
FERRARI
Shall we draw up the papers, or is our handshake good enough?
RICK
It's certainly not good enough. But since I'm in a hurry, it'll have to do.
Ferrari pours a cup for Rick, who takes a sip.
FERRARI
Ah, to get out of Casablanca and go to America! You're a lucky man.
RICK
Oh, by the way, my agreement with Sam's always been that he gets twenty-five percent of the profits. That still goes.
FERRARI
Hmmm. I happen to know that he gets ten percent. But he's worth twenty-five.
RICK
And Abdul and Carl and Sacha, they stay with the place, or I don't sell.
FERRARI
Of course they stay. Rick's wouldn't be Rick's without them.
RICK
Well, so long.
Rick gets up, followed by Ferrari. They shake hands to seal the deal.
He walks to the door, then stops and turns around.
RICK
Don't forget, you owe Rick's a hundred cartons of American cigarettes.
FERRARI
I shall remember to pay it-- to myself.
Rick leaves. Ferrari picks up a fly swatter from the table and swats at a fly.
CUT TO:
EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT
A car pulls quickly to a stop just outside the cafe.
On the door a huge placard reads:
CLOSED
By Order of the Prefect of Police
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
Rick sits at a table inside and reads the letters of transit. He hears a KNOCK on the door and puts them away in his pocket. He opens the door and Renault walks in.
RICK
You're late.
RENAULT
I was informed just as Laszlo was about to leave the hotel, so I knew I'd be on time.
RICK
I thought I asked you to tie up your watchdogs.
RENAULT
Oh, he won't be followed here.
Renault looks around the empty cafe.
RENAULT
You know, this place will never be the same without you, Ricky.
RICK
Yes, I know what you mean, but I've already spoken to Ferrari. You'll still win at roulette.
RENAULT
Is everything ready?
Rick points at his breast pocket.
RICK
I have the letters right here.
RENAULT
Tell me, when we searched the place, where were they?
RICK
Sam's piano.
RENAULT
Serves me right for not being musical.
They hear the CRUNCH of tires as a car pull up.
RICK
Oh. Here they are. You'd better wait in my office.
Renault walks up the stairs to Rick's office.
CUT TO:
EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT
Laszlo pays the cab driver. Ilsa quickly walks toward the entrance.
LASZLO
to driver
Here.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
Rick opens the door. Ilsa rushes in. Her intensity reveals the strain she is under. Rick grabs her by both arms and pulls her close.
ILSA
Richard, Victor thinks I'm leaving with him. Haven't you told him?
RICK
No, not yet.
ILSA
But it's all right, isn't it? You were able to arrange everything?
RICK
Everything is quite all right.
ILSA
Oh, Rick!
She looks at him with a vaguely questioning look.
RICK
We'll tell him at the airport. The less time to think, the easier for all of us. Please trust me.
Ilsa pauses and looks at Rick, unsure for a moment.
ILSA
Yes, I will.
Laszlo comes in and closes the door behind himself.
LASZLO
Monsieur Blaine, I don't know how to thank you.
RICK
Oh, save it. We've still lots of things to do.
They all walk towards the bar. Laszlo deposits his hat on a a nearby table.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - OFFICE - NIGHT
Renault opens the office door and peers down at the proceedings.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
LASZLO
I brought the money, Monsieur Blaine.
RICK
Keep it. You'll need it in America.
LASZLO
But we made a deal.
RICK
cutting him short
Oh, never mind about that. You won't have any trouble in Lisbon, will you?
LASZLO
No. It's all arranged.
RICK
Good. I've got the letters right here, all made out in blank.
He takes out the letters.
RICK
All you have to do is fill in the signatures.
He hands them to Laszlo, who takes them gratefully.
RENAULT
Victor Laszlo!
All three hear footsteps and turn to see Renault walking towards them from the bottom of the stairs.
RENAULT
Victor Laszlo, you are under arrest --
as he walks toward them
on a charge of accessory to the murder of the couriers from whom these letters were stolen.
Ilsa and Laszlo are both caught completely off guard. They turn towards Rick, bewildered. Horror is in Ilsa's eyes.
Renault takes the letters.
RENAULT
Oh, you are surprised about my friend Ricky?
Obviously the situation delights Renault. He smiles as he turns toward Rick.
RENAULT
The explanation is quite simple. Love, it seems, has triumphed over virtue. Thank --
Suddenly the smile fades. In Rick's hand is a gun, which he levels at Renault.
RICK
-- Not so fast, Louis. Nobody's going to be arrested. Not for a while yet.
RENAULT
Have you taken leave of your senses?
RICK
I have. Sit down over there.
RENAULT
Put that gun down.
Renault then walks toward Rick. Rick puts out his arm to stop him.
RICK
Louis, I wouldn't like to shoot you, but I will, if you take one more step.
Renault halts for a moment and studies Rick.
RENAULT
Under the circumstances, I will sit down.
He walks to a table and sits.
RICK
sharply
Keep your hands on the table.
He takes out a cigarette case.
RENAULT
I suppose you know what you're doing, but I wonder if you realize what this means?
RICK
I do. We've got plenty of time to discuss that later.
RENAULT
Call off your watch-dogs you said.
RICK
Just the same, you call the airport and let me hear you tell them. And remember, this gun's pointed right at your heart.
RENAULT
That is my least vulnerable spot.
As Renault picks up the phone and dials, Rick takes back the letters.
RENAULT
into phone
Hello, is this the airport? This is Captain Renault speaking. There'll be two letters of transit for the Lisbon plane. There's to be no trouble about them. Good.
CUT TO:
INT. GERMAN CONSULATE - NIGHT
Strasser is on the phone.
STRASSER
Hello? Hello?
He hangs up the receiver and presses a BUZZER on his desk. An officer quickly enters.
STRASSER
to officer
My car, quickly!
OFFICER
saluting
Zu Befehl, Herr Major.
The officer exits and Strasser resumes on the telephone.
STRASSER
This is Major Strasser. Have a squad of police meet me at the airport at once. At once! Do you hear?
He hangs up the receiver and, grabbing for his cap, hurriedly exits.
DISSOLVE TO:
EXT. AIRPORT - NIGHT
The entire airport is surrounded by a heavy fog. The outline of the transport plane is barely visible.
CUT TO:
INT/EXT. AIRPORT HANGAR - NIGHT
A uniformed ORDERLY uses a telephone near the hangar door. On the airfield a transport plane is being readied.
ORDERLY
Hello. Hello, radio tower? Lisbon plane taking off in ten minutes. East runway. Visibility: one and one half miles. Light ground fog. Depth of fog: approximately 500. Ceiling: unlimited. Thank you.
He hangs up and moves to a car that has just pulled up outside the hangar.
Renault gets out while the orderly stands at attention. He's closely followed by Rick, right hand in the pocket of his trench coat, covering Renault with a gun.
Laszlo and Ilsa emerge from the rear of the car.
RICK
indicating the orderly
Louis, have your man go with Mr. Laszlo and take care of his luggage.
RENAULT
bowing ironically
Certainly Rick, anything you say.
to orderly
Find Mr. Laszlo's luggage and put it it on the plane.
ORDERLY
Yes, sir. This way please.
The orderly escorts Laszlo off in the direction of the plane. Rick takes the letters of transit out of his pocket and hands them to Renault, who turns and walks toward the hangar.
RICK
If you don't mind, you fill in the names. That will make it even more official.
RENAULT
You think of everything, don't you?
RICK
quietly
And the names are Mr. and Mrs. Victor Laszlo.
Renault stops dead in his tracks, and turns around. Both Ilsa and Renault look at Rick with astonishment.
ILSA
But why my name, Richard?
RICK
Because you're getting on that plane.
ILSA
confused
I don't understand. What about you?
RICK
I'm staying here with him 'til the plane gets safely away.
Rick's intention suddenly dawns on Ilsa.
ILSA
No, Richard, no. What has happened to you? Last night we said --
RICK
-- Last night we said a great many things. You said I was to do the thinking for both of us. Well, I've done a lot of it since then and it all adds up to one thing. You're getting on that plane with Victor where you belong.
ILSA
protesting
But Richard, no, I, I --
RICK
-- You've got to listen to me. Do you have any idea what you'd have to look forward to if you stayed here? Nine chances out of ten we'd both wind up in a concentration camp. Isn't that true, Louis?
Renault countersigns the papers.
RENAULT
I'm afraid Major Strasser would insist.
ILSA
You're saying this only to make me go.
RICK
I'm saying it because it's true. Inside of us we both know you belong with Victor. You're part of his work, the thing that keeps him going. If that plane leaves the ground and you're not with him, you'll regret it.
ILSA
No.
RICK
Maybe not today, maybe not tomorrow, but soon, and for the rest of your life.
ILSA
But what about us?
RICK
We'll always have Paris. We didn't have, we'd lost it, until you came to Casablanca. We got it back last night.
ILSA
And I said I would never leave you.
RICK
And you never will. But I've got a job to do, too. Where I'm going you can't follow. What I've got to do you can't be any part of. Ilsa, I'm no good at being noble, but it doesn't take much to see that the problems of three little people don't amount to a hill of beans in this crazy world. Someday you'll understand that. Now, now--
Ilsa's eyes well up with tears. Rick puts his hand to her chin and raises her face to meet his own.
RICK
Here's looking at you, kid.
CUT TO:
EXT. ROAD - NIGHT
Major Strasser drives at break-neck speed towards the airport. He HONKS his horn furiously.
CUT TO:
INT/EXT. AIRPORT HANGAR - NIGHT
Laszlo returns. Rick walks into the hangar and Renault hands him the letters. He walks back out to Laszlo.
LASZLO
Everything in order?
RICK
All except one thing. There's something you should know before you leave.
LASZLO
sensing what is coming
Monsieur Blaine, I don't ask you to explain anything.
RICK
I'm going to anyway, because it may make a difference to you later on. You said you knew about Ilsa and me.
LASZLO
Yes.
RICK
But you didn't know she was at my place last night when you were. She came there for the letters of transit. Isn't that true, Ilsa?
ILSA
facing Laszlo
Yes.
RICK
forcefully
She tried everything to get them, and nothing worked. She did her best to convince me that she was still in love with me, but that was all over long ago. For your sake, she pretended it wasn't, and I let her pretend.
LASZLO
I understand.
RICK
Here it is.
Rick hands the letters to Laszlo.
LASZLO
Thanks. I appreciate it.
Laszlo extends his hand to Rick, who grasps it firmly.
LASZLO
And welcome back to the fight. This time I know our side will win.
On the airfield the airplane engine TURNS OVER and the propellers start turning. They all turn to see the plane readying for take-off.
Ilsa looks at Rick and he returns her stare with a blank expression. He then glances at Laszlo, as does Ilsa.
Then Laszlo breaks the silence.
LASZLO
Are you ready Ilsa?
ILSA
Yes, I'm ready.
to Rick
Goodbye, Rick. God bless you.
RICK
You better hurry, or you'll miss that plane.
Rick watches as Ilsa and Laszlo walk very deliberately towards the plane.
RENAULT
Well I was right. You are a sentimentalist.
RICK
Stay where you are. I don't know what you're talking about.
Rick puts a cigarette in his mouth.
RENAULT
What you just did for Laszlo, and that fairy tale that you invented to send Ilsa away with him. I know a little about women, my friend. She went, but she knew you were lying.
RICK
Anyway, thanks for helping me out.
RENAULT
I suppose you know this isn't going to be pleasant for either of us, especially for you. I'll have to arrest you of course.
RICK
As soon as the plane goes, Louis.
The door to the plane is closed by an attendant and it slowly taxies down the field.
Suddenly a speeding car comes to a stop outside the hangar. Strasser alights from the car and runs toward Renault.
STRASSER
What is the meaning of that phone call?
RENAULT
Victor Laszlo is on that plane.
Renault nods toward the field. Strasser turns to see the plane taxiing towards the runway.
STRASSER
Why do you stand here? Why don't you stop him?
RENAULT
Ask Monsieur Rick.
Strasser looks briefly at Rick, then makes a step towards the telephone just inside the hangar door.
RICK
Get away from that phone.
Strasser stops in his tracks, looks at Rick, and sees that he is armed.
STRASSER
steely
I would advise you not to interfere.
RICK
I was willing to shoot Captain Renault, and I'm willing to shoot you.
Strasser watches the plane in agony. His eyes dart towards the telephone. He runs toward it and desperately grabs the receiver.
STRASSER
Hello?
RICK
Put that phone down!
STRASSER
Get me the Radio Tower!
RICK
Put it down!
Strasser, one hand holding the receiver, pulls out a pistol with the other hand, and SHOOTS quickly at Rick. The bullet misses its mark.
Rick now SHOOTS at Strasser, who crumples to the ground.
At the sound of an approaching car both men turn. A police car SPEEDS in and comes to a stop near Renault. Four gendarmes hurriedly jump out.
In the distance the plane turns onto the runway.
The gendarmes run to Renault. The first one hurriedly salutes him.
GENDARME
Mon Capitaine!
RENAULT
Major Strasser's been shot.
Renault pauses and looks at Rick. Rick returns Renault's gaze with expressionless eyes.
RENAULT
Round up the usual suspects.
GENDARME
Oui, mon Capitaine.
The gendarmes take Strasser's body away and then drive off.
Renault walks inside the hangar, picks up a bottle of Vichy water, and opens it.
RENAULT
Well, Rick, you're not only a sentimentalist, but you've become a patriot.
RICK
Maybe, but it seemed like a good time to start.
RENAULT
I think perhaps you're right.
As he pours the water into a glass, Renault sees the Vichy label and quickly DROPS the bottle into a trash basket which he then KICKS over.
He walks over and stands beside Rick. They both watch the plane take off, maintaining their gaze until it disappears into the clouds.
Rick and Louis slowly walk away from the hangar toward the runway.
RENAULT
It might be a good idea for you to disappear from Casablanca for a while. There's a Free French garrison over at Brazzaville. I could be induced to arrange a passage.
RICK
My letter of transit? I could use a trip. But it doesn't make any difference about our bet. You still owe me ten thousand francs.
RENAULT
And that ten thousand francs should pay our expenses.
RICK
Our expenses?
RENAULT
Uh huh.
RICK
Louis, I think this is the beginning of a beautiful friendship.
The two walk off together into the night.
FADE OUT.
THE END