<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
CUT TO:
INT. RENAULT'S OFFICE - MORNING
Renault sits at his desk and smokes while Rick nervously fingers his hat. They're interrupted by an orderly.
Renault hands some forms to the orderly, who then exits, and the conversation continues.
RICK
But you haven't any actual proof, and you know it. This isn't Germany or occupied France. All you can do is fine him a few thousand francs and give him thirty days. You might as well let him go now.
RENAULT
Ricky, I'd advise you not to be too interested in what happens to Laszlo. If by any chance you were to help him escape --
RICK
-- What makes you think I'd stick my neck out for Laszlo?
RENAULT
Because one, you've bet ten thousand francs he'd escape. Two, you have the letters of transit, now don't bother to deny it. And, well, you might do it simply because you don't like Strasser's looks. As a matter of fact, I don't like him either.
RICK
Well, they're all excellent reasons.
RENAULT
Don't count too much on my friendship, Ricky. In this matter I'm powerless. Besides, I might lose ten thousand francs.
RICK
You're not very subtle, but you are effective. I, I get the point. Yes, I have the letters, but I intend using them myself. I'm leaving Casablanca on tonight's plane, the last plane.
RENAULT
Huh?
RICK
And I'm taking a friend with me. One you'll appreciate.
RENAULT
What friend?
RICK
Ilsa Lund.
pause
That ought to put your mind to rest about my helping Laszlo escape. The last man I want to see in America.
RENAULT
You didn't come here to tell me this. You have the letters of transit. You can fill in your name and hers and leave any time you please. Why are you interested in what happens to Laszlo?
Renault gets out of his chair and crosses to the front of his desk.
RICK
I'm not. But I am interested in what happens to Ilsa and me. We have a legal right to go, that's true. But people have been held in Casablanca in spite of their legal rights.
Renault retrieves a fresh cigarette from a box on his desk.
RENAULT
What makes you think we want to hold you?
Renault chain-lights his new cigarette with the old one.
RICK
Ilsa is Laszlo's wife. She probably knows things that Strasser would like to know. Louis, I'll make a deal with you. Instead of this petty charge you have against him, you can get something really big, something that would chuck him in a concentration camp for years. That would be quite a feather in your cap, wouldn't it?
RENAULT
It certainly would. Germany-- Vichy would be very grateful.
RICK
Then release him. You be at my place a half hour before the plane leaves.
Renault sits back down in his chair.
RICK
I'll arrange to have Laszlo come there to pick up the letters of transit, and that'll give you the criminal grounds on which to make the arrest. You get him, and we get away. To the Germans that last will be just a minor annoyance.
RENAULT
puzzled
There's still something about this business I don't quite understand. Miss Lund, she's very beautiful, yes, but you were never interested in any woman.
RICK
Well, she isn't just any woman.
Rick stares at the floor, then looks back up at Renault.
RENAULT
I see. How do I know you'll keep your end of the bargain?
RICK
I'll make the arrangements right now with Laszlo in the visitor's pen.
RENAULT
Ricky, I'm going to miss you. Apparently you're the only one in Casablanca who has even less scruples than I.
RICK
Oh, thanks.
RENAULT
Go ahead, Ricky.
Renault presses a button on his desk, triggering a BUZZER.
The door to Renault's office opens. Rick rises to go.
RICK
And by the way, call off your watchdogs when you let him go. I don't want them around this afternoon. I'm taking no chances, Louis, not even with you.
CUT TO:
INT. THE BLUE PARROT - DAY
A waiter brings tea to Rick and Ferrari, who sit alone at a table in a secluded nook off the main room.
FERRARI
Shall we draw up the papers, or is our handshake good enough?
RICK
It's certainly not good enough. But since I'm in a hurry, it'll have to do.
Ferrari pours a cup for Rick, who takes a sip.
FERRARI
Ah, to get out of Casablanca and go to America! You're a lucky man.
RICK
Oh, by the way, my agreement with Sam's always been that he gets twenty-five percent of the profits. That still goes.
FERRARI
Hmmm. I happen to know that he gets ten percent. But he's worth twenty-five.
RICK
And Abdul and Carl and Sacha, they stay with the place, or I don't sell.
FERRARI
Of course they stay. Rick's wouldn't be Rick's without them.
RICK
Well, so long.
Rick gets up, followed by Ferrari. They shake hands to seal the deal.
He walks to the door, then stops and turns around.
RICK
Don't forget, you owe Rick's a hundred cartons of American cigarettes.
FERRARI
I shall remember to pay it-- to myself.
Rick leaves. Ferrari picks up a fly swatter from the table and swats at a fly.
CUT TO:
EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT
A car pulls quickly to a stop just outside the cafe.
On the door a huge placard reads:
CLOSED
By Order of the Prefect of Police
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
Rick sits at a table inside and reads the letters of transit. He hears a KNOCK on the door and puts them away in his pocket. He opens the door and Renault walks in.
RICK
You're late.
RENAULT
I was informed just as Laszlo was about to leave the hotel, so I knew I'd be on time.
RICK
I thought I asked you to tie up your watchdogs.
RENAULT
Oh, he won't be followed here.
Renault looks around the empty cafe.
RENAULT
You know, this place will never be the same without you, Ricky.
RICK
Yes, I know what you mean, but I've already spoken to Ferrari. You'll still win at roulette.
RENAULT
Is everything ready?
Rick points at his breast pocket.
RICK
I have the letters right here.
RENAULT
Tell me, when we searched the place, where were they?
RICK
Sam's piano.
RENAULT
Serves me right for not being musical.
They hear the CRUNCH of tires as a car pull up.
RICK
Oh. Here they are. You'd better wait in my office.
Renault walks up the stairs to Rick's office.
CUT TO:
EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT
Laszlo pays the cab driver. Ilsa quickly walks toward the entrance.
LASZLO
to driver
Here.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
Rick opens the door. Ilsa rushes in. Her intensity reveals the strain she is under. Rick grabs her by both arms and pulls her close.
ILSA
Richard, Victor thinks I'm leaving with him. Haven't you told him?
RICK
No, not yet.
ILSA
But it's all right, isn't it? You were able to arrange everything?
RICK
Everything is quite all right.
ILSA
Oh, Rick!
She looks at him with a vaguely questioning look.
RICK
We'll tell him at the airport. The less time to think, the easier for all of us. Please trust me.
Ilsa pauses and looks at Rick, unsure for a moment.
ILSA
Yes, I will.
Laszlo comes in and closes the door behind himself.
LASZLO
Monsieur Blaine, I don't know how to thank you.
RICK
Oh, save it. We've still lots of things to do.
They all walk towards the bar. Laszlo deposits his hat on a a nearby table.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - OFFICE - NIGHT
Renault opens the office door and peers down at the proceedings.
CUT TO:
INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT
LASZLO
I brought the money, Monsieur Blaine.
RICK
Keep it. You'll need it in America.
LASZLO
But we made a deal.
RICK
cutting him short
Oh, never mind about that. You won't have any trouble in Lisbon, will you?
LASZLO
No. It's all arranged.
RICK
Good. I've got the letters right here, all made out in blank.
He takes out the letters.
RICK
All you have to do is fill in the signatures.
He hands them to Laszlo, who takes them gratefully.
RENAULT
Victor Laszlo!
All three hear footsteps and turn to see Renault walking towards them from the bottom of the stairs.
RENAULT
Victor Laszlo, you are under arrest --
as he walks toward them
on a charge of accessory to the murder of the couriers from whom these letters were stolen.
Ilsa and Laszlo are both caught completely off guard. They turn towards Rick, bewildered. Horror is in Ilsa's eyes.
Renault takes the letters.
RENAULT
Oh, you are surprised about my friend Ricky?
Obviously the situation delights Renault. He smiles as he turns toward Rick.
RENAULT
The explanation is quite simple. Love, it seems, has triumphed over virtue. Thank --
Suddenly the smile fades. In Rick's hand is a gun, which he levels at Renault.
RICK
-- Not so fast, Louis. Nobody's going to be arrested. Not for a while yet.
RENAULT
Have you taken leave of your senses?
RICK
I have. Sit down over there.
RENAULT
Put that gun down.
Renault then walks toward Rick. Rick puts out his arm to stop him.
RICK
Louis, I wouldn't like to shoot you, but I will, if you take one more step.
Renault halts for a moment and studies Rick.
RENAULT
Under the circumstances, I will sit down.
He walks to a table and sits.
RICK
sharply
Keep your hands on the table.
He takes out a cigarette case.
RENAULT
I suppose you know what you're doing, but I wonder if you realize what this means?
RICK
I do. We've got plenty of time to discuss that later.
RENAULT
Call off your watch-dogs you said.
RICK
Just the same, you call the airport and let me hear you tell them. And remember, this gun's pointed right at your heart.
RENAULT
That is my least vulnerable spot.
As Renault picks up the phone and dials, Rick takes back the letters.
RENAULT
into phone
Hello, is this the airport? This is Captain Renault speaking. There'll be two letters of transit for the Lisbon plane. There's to be no trouble about them. Good.
CUT TO:
INT. GERMAN CONSULATE - NIGHT
Strasser is on the phone.
STRASSER
Hello? Hello?
He hangs up the receiver and presses a BUZZER on his desk. An officer quickly enters.
STRASSER
to officer
My car, quickly!
OFFICER
saluting
Zu Befehl, Herr Major.
The officer exits and Strasser resumes on the telephone.
STRASSER
This is Major Strasser. Have a squad of police meet me at the airport at once. At once! Do you hear?
He hangs up the receiver and, grabbing for his cap, hurriedly exits.
DISSOLVE TO:
EXT. AIRPORT - NIGHT
The entire airport is surrounded by a heavy fog. The outline of the transport plane is barely visible.
CUT TO:
INT/EXT. AIRPORT HANGAR - NIGHT
A uniformed ORDERLY uses a telephone near the hangar door. On the airfield a transport plane is being readied.
ORDERLY
Hello. Hello, radio tower? Lisbon plane taking off in ten minutes. East runway. Visibility: one and one half miles. Light ground fog. Depth of fog: approximately 500. Ceiling: unlimited. Thank you.
He hangs up and moves to a car that has just pulled up outside the hangar.
Renault gets out while the orderly stands at attention. He's closely followed by Rick, right hand in the pocket of his trench coat, covering Renault with a gun.
Laszlo and Ilsa emerge from the rear of the car.
RICK
indicating the orderly
Louis, have your man go with Mr. Laszlo and take care of his luggage.
RENAULT
bowing ironically
Certainly Rick, anything you say.
to orderly
Find Mr. Laszlo's luggage and put it it on the plane.
ORDERLY
Yes, sir. This way please.
The orderly escorts Laszlo off in the direction of the plane. Rick takes the letters of transit out of his pocket and hands them to Renault, who turns and walks toward the hangar.
RICK
If you don't mind, you fill in the names. That will make it even more official.
RENAULT
You think of everything, don't you?
RICK
quietly
And the names are Mr. and Mrs. Victor Laszlo.
Renault stops dead in his tracks, and turns around. Both Ilsa and Renault look at Rick with astonishment.
ILSA
But why my name, Richard?
RICK
Because you're getting on that plane.
ILSA
confused
I don't understand. What about you?
RICK
I'm staying here with him 'til the plane gets safely away.
Rick's intention suddenly dawns on Ilsa.
ILSA
No, Richard, no. What has happened to you? Last night we said --
RICK
-- Last night we said a great many things. You said I was to do the thinking for both of us. Well, I've done a lot of it since then and it all adds up to one thing. You're getting on that plane with Victor where you belong.
ILSA
protesting
But Richard, no, I, I --
RICK
-- You've got to listen to me. Do you have any idea what you'd have to look forward to if you stayed here? Nine chances out of ten we'd both wind up in a concentration camp. Isn't that true, Louis?
Renault countersigns the papers.
RENAULT
I'm afraid Major Strasser would insist.
ILSA
You're saying this only to make me go.
RICK
I'm saying it because it's true. Inside of us we both know you belong with Victor. You're part of his work, the thing that keeps him going. If that plane leaves the ground and you're not with him, you'll regret it.
ILSA
No.
RICK
Maybe not today, maybe not tomorrow, but soon, and for the rest of your life.
ILSA
But what about us?
RICK
We'll always have Paris. We didn't have, we'd lost it, until you came to Casablanca. We got it back last night.
ILSA
And I said I would never leave you.
RICK
And you never will. But I've got a job to do, too. Where I'm going you can't follow. What I've got to do you can't be any part of. Ilsa, I'm no good at being noble, but it doesn't take much to see that the problems of three little people don't amount to a hill of beans in this crazy world. Someday you'll understand that. Now, now--
Ilsa's eyes well up with tears. Rick puts his hand to her chin and raises her face to meet his own.
RICK
Here's looking at you, kid.
CUT TO:
EXT. ROAD - NIGHT
Major Strasser drives at break-neck speed towards the airport. He HONKS his horn furiously.
CUT TO:
INT/EXT. AIRPORT HANGAR - NIGHT
Laszlo returns. Rick walks into the hangar and Renault hands him the letters. He walks back out to Laszlo.
LASZLO
Everything in order?
RICK
All except one thing. There's something you should know before you leave.
LASZLO
sensing what is coming
Monsieur Blaine, I don't ask you to explain anything.
RICK
I'm going to anyway, because it may make a difference to you later on. You said you knew about Ilsa and me.
LASZLO
Yes.
RICK
But you didn't know she was at my place last night when you were. She came there for the letters of transit. Isn't that true, Ilsa?
ILSA
facing Laszlo
Yes.
RICK
forcefully
She tried everything to get them, and nothing worked. She did her best to convince me that she was still in love with me, but that was all over long ago. For your sake, she pretended it wasn't, and I let her pretend.
LASZLO
I understand.
RICK
Here it is.
Rick hands the letters to Laszlo.
LASZLO
Thanks. I appreciate it.
Laszlo extends his hand to Rick, who grasps it firmly.
LASZLO
And welcome back to the fight. This time I know our side will win.
On the airfield the airplane engine TURNS OVER and the propellers start turning. They all turn to see the plane readying for take-off.
Ilsa looks at Rick and he returns her stare with a blank expression. He then glances at Laszlo, as does Ilsa.
Then Laszlo breaks the silence.
LASZLO
Are you ready Ilsa?
ILSA
Yes, I'm ready.
to Rick
Goodbye, Rick. God bless you.
RICK
You better hurry, or you'll miss that plane.
Rick watches as Ilsa and Laszlo walk very deliberately towards the plane.
RENAULT
Well I was right. You are a sentimentalist.
RICK
Stay where you are. I don't know what you're talking about.
Rick puts a cigarette in his mouth.
RENAULT
What you just did for Laszlo, and that fairy tale that you invented to send Ilsa away with him. I know a little about women, my friend. She went, but she knew you were lying.
RICK
Anyway, thanks for helping me out.
RENAULT
I suppose you know this isn't going to be pleasant for either of us, especially for you. I'll have to arrest you of course.
RICK
As soon as the plane goes, Louis.
The door to the plane is closed by an attendant and it slowly taxies down the field.
Suddenly a speeding car comes to a stop outside the hangar. Strasser alights from the car and runs toward Renault.
STRASSER
What is the meaning of that phone call?
RENAULT
Victor Laszlo is on that plane.
Renault nods toward the field. Strasser turns to see the plane taxiing towards the runway.
STRASSER
Why do you stand here? Why don't you stop him?
RENAULT
Ask Monsieur Rick.
Strasser looks briefly at Rick, then makes a step towards the telephone just inside the hangar door.
RICK
Get away from that phone.
Strasser stops in his tracks, looks at Rick, and sees that he is armed.
STRASSER
steely
I would advise you not to interfere.
RICK
I was willing to shoot Captain Renault, and I'm willing to shoot you.
Strasser watches the plane in agony. His eyes dart towards the telephone. He runs toward it and desperately grabs the receiver.
STRASSER
Hello?
RICK
Put that phone down!
STRASSER
Get me the Radio Tower!
RICK
Put it down!
Strasser, one hand holding the receiver, pulls out a pistol with the other hand, and SHOOTS quickly at Rick. The bullet misses its mark.
Rick now SHOOTS at Strasser, who crumples to the ground.
At the sound of an approaching car both men turn. A police car SPEEDS in and comes to a stop near Renault. Four gendarmes hurriedly jump out.
In the distance the plane turns onto the runway.
The gendarmes run to Renault. The first one hurriedly salutes him.
GENDARME
Mon Capitaine!
RENAULT
Major Strasser's been shot.
Renault pauses and looks at Rick. Rick returns Renault's gaze with expressionless eyes.
RENAULT
Round up the usual suspects.
GENDARME
Oui, mon Capitaine.
The gendarmes take Strasser's body away and then drive off.
Renault walks inside the hangar, picks up a bottle of Vichy water, and opens it.
RENAULT
Well, Rick, you're not only a sentimentalist, but you've become a patriot.
RICK
Maybe, but it seemed like a good time to start.
RENAULT
I think perhaps you're right.
As he pours the water into a glass, Renault sees the Vichy label and quickly DROPS the bottle into a trash basket which he then KICKS over.
He walks over and stands beside Rick. They both watch the plane take off, maintaining their gaze until it disappears into the clouds.
Rick and Louis slowly walk away from the hangar toward the runway.
RENAULT
It might be a good idea for you to disappear from Casablanca for a while. There's a Free French garrison over at Brazzaville. I could be induced to arrange a passage.
RICK
My letter of transit? I could use a trip. But it doesn't make any difference about our bet. You still owe me ten thousand francs.
RENAULT
And that ten thousand francs should pay our expenses.
RICK
Our expenses?
RENAULT
Uh huh.
RICK
Louis, I think this is the beginning of a beautiful friendship.
The two walk off together into the night.
FADE OUT.
THE END

