<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="Casablanca-Project/versioning/versioningschema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <metadata>
        <fileDesc>
            <title>Versioning experiment with Casablanca Scripts</title>
            <editor>Sean Martin</editor>
            <desc>I am hoping to explore how the ending for the play Everbody Comes To Rick's compares to two different drafts of the ending for Casablanca.</desc>
        </fileDesc>
        <sourceDesc> 
            <listWit>
                <witness xml:id="everybody-play"><p>This is the original stage play on which the movie Casablanca was based. 
                    In the PDF photo facsimile provided by the Internet Archive at <ptr target="https://archive.org/details/everybody-comes-to-ricks"/> and other locations 
                    including <ptr target="http://vincasa.com/Screenplay-Everybody_Comes_to_Rick%27s.pdf"/>, this information is marked digitally in a red box. </p>
                    
                    <p>The title is given is <title>EVERYBODY COMES TO RICK’S</title> By: <author>MURRAY BURNETT</author> and <author>JOAN ALISON</author>.</p>
                    
                    <p>There is a print address on the script reading: 
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>WHARTON &amp; GABEL,</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>11 West 42nd Street,</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>New York, New York.</addrLine>
                            <idno>LA 4-8335</idno>
                        </address></p>
                    <p> We also see a handwritten
                        address on the bottom right reading: 
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Writer’s Guild of Am<unclear><supplied>erica</supplied></unclear></addrLine>
                            <addrLine>22 West 48th St.</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>New York 36, N.Y.</addrLine>           
                        </address> </p>
                </witness>
                <witness xml:id="77-scene-alt">This is an undated script that we found on
                    <ptr target="https://app.studiobinder.com/company/580e85847e7982164664e844/collab/5eac35a683f7a90bfc3fc810/projects/5de590454f452c09a98e975b/document/5de5904f1fe52b06c2f4bd79/%5Bobject%20Object%5D?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=sb-app-link&amp;utm_campaign=script&amp;utm_term=casablanca-script-breakdown&amp;utm_content=full-script-pdf-download"/> 
                    that has numbered scenes up to 77. It is uncertain whether this script comes before or after the dated June 1, 1942 script.
                </witness>
                <witness xml:id="1942-06-01-screenplay">This is a screenplay of unknown provenience that we found at
                    <ptr target="https://mckeestory.com/wp-content/uploads/Digital-CASABLANCA.pdf"/> and has numbered scenes up to 285. It appears also appears to be
                    a better photo facsimile but the same copy as the 1942 script archived on Script slug at 
                    <ptr target="https://assets.scriptslug.com/live/pdf/scripts/casablanca-1942.pdf"/>.
                </witness>
            </listWit></sourceDesc>
        
        
    </metadata>
    <script>
        <scene>
           <app> <rdg wit="77-scene-alt"><dir> Strasser watches the plane in agony. His eyes dart towards the
                telephone. He runs
                toward it and desperately grabs the receiver.</dir></rdg>
               <rdg wit="1942-06-01-screenplay"><scene n="275">MED. SHOT - NEAR HANGAR</scene><dir>Strasser watches the plane in agony. His eyes dart toward the telephone.</dir>
                   <scene n="276">CLOSE SHOT - RENAULT</scene><dir>He watches fascinated.</dir>
                   <scene n="277">MED. SHOT - RICK AND STRASSER</scene><dir>Strasser runs toward the telephone.</dir></rdg>
               <rdg wit="everybody-play"><act n="3"/><sp><speaker who="sam">Sam</speaker>
                   <diag><dir>who sees the gun and stops</dir> Whut's de trouble, boss?</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="rick">Rick</speaker>
                   <diag>No trouble, Sam. The Captain and I want to hear a little music. Get over to the piano, but take care when you step across the line of fire.</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="sam">Sam</speaker>
                   <diag><dir>perplexed, but obeying</dir>Yassuh.</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="rin">Rinaldo</speaker>
                   <diag>May I go now? I do not wish to listen to music,</diag></sp>
                  <sp> <speaker who="rick">Rick</speaker>
                   <diag>No.</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="rin">Rinaldo</speaker>
                  <diag> But this is absurd. They have left. There is no reason for holding me here.</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="rick">Rick</speaker>
                   <diag>Just for a little while, Luis. There's still the telephone!</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="rick">Rick Cont</speaker>
                   <diag><dir>The RABBIT has seated himself at piano and starts to improvise rather softly</dir> Louder, and faster, Sam. Make it hot. <dir>The RABBIT increases the tempo, swinging very loud and fast. Music swells, gets wilder</dir></diag></sp>
                  <sp><speaker who="rin"> Rinaldo</speaker>
                   <diag><descr>Hysterically</descr> Must you play!</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="rick">Rick</speaker>
                   <diag>Keep playing, Sam. <dir>The RABBIT obeys, and suddenly the sound of a plane motor cuts across the noise of piano. Both RICK and RINALDO look up. The music stops</dir></diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="rin">Rinaldo</speaker>
                   <diag>The Lisbon plane.</diag></sp>
                  <sp><speaker who="rick">Rick</speaker>
                  <diag> And that lets you out.<dir> Before either of them can move, the door bursts open and STRASSER rushes in. He is in a towering rage</dir></diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="str">Strasser</speaker>
                  <diag> You imbecile! You stupid swine! They're gone! They were on that plane!</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="rin">Rinaldo</speaker>
                   <diag>I know it.</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="str">Strasser</speaker>
                   <diag>And your fine neutral here. He's responsible. <dir>Then he sees the gun and checks. RICK takes the gun and points it very deliberately at Strasser</dir></diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="rick">Rick</speaker>
                   <diag>At the present moment, I am debating very seriously with myself the question of killing you. I don't see any reason why I shouldn't except -- that I have never killed a man. <dir>He throws the gun contemptuously on table. STRASSER leaps for it and covers Rick.</dir></diag></sp>
                  <sp> <speaker who="str">Strasser</speaker>
                   <diag>You are under arrest.</diag></sp>
                  <sp> <speaker who="rick">Rick</speaker>
                   <diag><descr>Coolly</descr> Not really. <dir>He rises slowly. The RABBIT watches him with agonized eyes</dir></diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="str">Strasser</speaker>
                   <diag>I am waiting.</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker>Rick</speaker>
                  <diag><dir> Starts walking slowly towards door</dir> So long, Sam. I'd go over to the Blue Parrot, if I were you <dir>As he passes Rinaldo, who has not moved</dir></diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker who="rin">Rinaldo</speaker>
                   <diag>Why did you do it, Rick?</diag></sp>
                   <sp><speaker>Rick</speaker>
                   <diag><descr>Pausing</descr> For the folding money, Luis, for the folding money. You owe me five thousand francs. <dir>RICK walks out with STRASSER as the
                   
                   
                   
                   
                   CURTAIN FALLS</dir></diag></sp></rdg>
           </app>
            <app><rdg wit="77-scene-alt"><sp>
                <speaker who="str"> STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Hello? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker> 
                <diag> Put that phone down! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Get me the Radio Tower! </diag>
            </sp>
             <sp>
                 <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                 <diag> Put it down! </diag>
             </sp>
            </rdg>
                <rdg wit="1942-06-01-screenplay"><scene n="278">CLOSE SHOT - AT TELEPHONE</scene><dir>Strasser desperately grasps the receiver.</dir> 
                <sp><speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag><descr>into phone</descr>Hello... Hello...</diag></sp>
                    <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK'S VOICE</speaker>
                    <diag><descr>over scene</descr>Put that phone down!</diag></sp>
                    <sp><speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                    <diag><descr>into phone</descr> Get me the Radio Tower.</diag></sp>
                    <scene n="278">CLOSE SHOT - AT TELEPHONE</scene>
                    <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker></sp>
                    <diag>Put it down.</diag>
                </rdg>
            </app>
            <dir>
                Strasser, one hand holding
                        the receiver,
                        pulls out a pistol with the other hand, and SHOOTS quickly
                        at Rick. The
                        bullet misses its mark. Rick now SHOOTS at Strasser, who
                        crumples to the
                        ground. 
                        <app><rdg wit="77-scene-alt">At the sound of an approaching car both men turn. A
                        police car
                        SPEEDS in and comes to a stop near Renault. Four gendarmes
                        hurriedly jump
                        out. In the distance the plane turns onto the runway. The
                        gendarmes run to
                        Renault. The first one hurriedly salutes him.</rdg></app>
                <app><rdg wit="1942-06-01-screenplay"><scene n="279">MED. SHOT - RICK AND RENAULT</scene><dir>Renault continues to stare off scene. Rick watches upward, as the SOUND of the plane becomes fainter.</dir>
                <scene n="280">LONG SHOT - SKY</scene><dir>The Transport grows smaller in the distance.</dir>
                <scene n="281">MED. SHOT - NEAR HANGAR</scene><dir>Rick continues to stare aloft. At the SOUND of a car approaching, both men turn.</dir>
                <scene n="282">LONG SHOT - A POLICE CAR</scene><dir>speeds in and comes to a stop near Renault. Four police hurriedly alight.</dir>
                <scene n="283">CLOSE SHOT - RENAULT</scene><dir>looking at Rick.</dir>
                <scene n="284">CLOSE SHOT - RICK</scene><dir>as he returns Renault's gaze. His eyes are expressionless.</dir>
                <scene n="285">FULL SHOT</scene><dir>The gendarmes run to Renault. Renault returns to them.</dir></rdg></app>
            </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="gen">GENDARME</speaker>
                <diag> Mon Capitaine! </diag>
            </sp>
            <app><rdg wit="77-scene-alt"><sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Major Strasser's been shot. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault pauses and looks at Rick. Rick returns Renault's gaze with
                expressionless
                eyes.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Round up the usual suspects. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="gen">GENDARME</speaker>
                <diag> Oui, mon Capitaine. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The gendarmes take Strasser's body away and then drive off.
                Renault walks inside
                the hangar, picks up a bottle of Vichy water, and opens it. </dir></rdg>
            <rdg n="1942-06-01-screenplay">
                <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>Major Strasser has been shot.<descr>pauses as he looks at Rick, then to the gendarmes</descr>Round up the usual suspects...</diag></sp>
                <sp><speaker who="gen">GENDARME</speaker>
                <diag><descr>saluting</descr>Yes, Captain.</diag>
                <dir>He leads the other gendarmes off. The two men look at one another.</dir></sp>
            </rdg></app>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Well, Rick, you're not only a sentimentalist, but you've
                    become a patriot.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Maybe, but it seemed like a good time to start. </diag>
            </sp>
            <app><rdg wit="77-scene-alt"><sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I think perhaps you're right. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>As he pours the water into a glass, Renault sees the Vichy label
                and quickly DROPS
                the bottle into a trash basket which he then KICKS over. He walks
                over and stands
                beside Rick. They both watch the plane take off, maintaining their
                gaze until it
                disappears into the clouds. Rick and Louis slowly walk away from
                the hangar toward
                the runway.</dir></rdg>
                <rdg wit="1942-06-01-screenplay">
                    <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                        <diag><descr>lights a cigarette</descr>It might be just as well for you to disappear from Casablanca. I understand there's a Free French garrison over at Bravvaville. I might be induced to arrange your passage.</diag></sp>
            </rdg></app>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> It might be a good idea for you to disappear from Casablanca
                    for a while.
                    There's a Free French garrison over at Brazzaville. I could be
                    induced to
                    arrange a passage. </diag>
            </sp>
            <app><rdg wit="77-scene-alt"><sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> My letter of transit? I could use a trip. But it doesn't
                    make any difference
                    about our bet. You still owe me ten thousand francs. </diag>
            </sp></rdg>
            <rdg wit="1942-06-01-screenplay"><sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag><descr>smiles</descr>My Letter of Transit? <descr>his eyes following the plane, which is now receding into the distance</descr>I could use a trip... But it doesn't make any difference about our bet, you still owe me the ten thousand francs.</diag>
            </sp></rdg></app>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> And that ten thousand francs should pay our expenses.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Our expenses? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Uh huh. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Louis, I think this is the beginning of a beautiful
                    friendship. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir><app><rdg wit="77-scene-alt">The two walk off together into the night. </rdg></app>FADE OUT: THE END </dir>
        </scene>
    </script>
</xml>